<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-02-20T04:43:37-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">From the Ashes</title><subtitle>An Ironsworn blog</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Worldbuilding Part III - External Forces</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/worldbuilding-part-iii-external-forces/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Worldbuilding Part III - External Forces" /><published>2019-02-20T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-02-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/worldbuilding-part-iii-external-forces</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/worldbuilding-part-iii-external-forces/">&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;/worldbuilding-part-i-the-land&quot;&gt;Part I&lt;/a&gt;, we discussed what the land is like, and a bit of history.
Then we learned some important things about our people in &lt;a href=&quot;worldbuilding-part-ii-the-people&quot;&gt;Part II&lt;/a&gt;.
Definitely check those out if you missed them, because they will inform many decisions we make moving forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this, our final piece of worldbuilding, we will learn about other peoples and dangers with which our freshly conceived dwarven society will have to contend.
As we will learn, the people of this broken land are definitely not alone, and certainly aren’t safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-firstborn&quot;&gt;The Firstborn&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world of Kalemin, as we discussed before, was originally envisioned to be a fairly standard fantasy setting, demographically speaking.
It is the kind of world in which you can find not only humans, but also dwarves, elves, gnomes, and the rest (even some catfolk if you know where to look).
This is not really a deviation from the Ironlands setting, as some of the options below will show.
Those other non-Ironlander (humans) peoples are referred to as Firstborn in that setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with any world in which there are many different cultures, there are eternal arguments among the races of Kalemin as to who came first, though everyone agrees that it definitely was not the humans.
The elves, at least during this time period, insist that they are the oldest race of note.
The dwarves counter that they’ve been around nearly as long as the mountains themselves.
The gnomes pretty much keep out of it because they don’t really care one way or another. In reality, it was the halflings, but that’s a tale for another game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point is that the term Firstborn is inaccurate for this game.
That’s still the category of this Truth, but you won’t hear anyone calling another group of people “firstborn” in this world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enough nattering on. Let’s have a look at the options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;FIRSTBORN&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The firstborn have passed into legend. Some say the remnants of the old tribes still dwell in deep forests or high mountains. Most believe they were never anything more than myth.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The firstborn live in isolation and are fiercely protective of their own lands.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The firstborn hold sway in the Ironlands. The elves of the deep forests and the giants of the hills tolerate us and even trade with us—for now. Ironlanders fear the day they decide we are no longer welcome here.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, we can strike the first option straight away.
The racial diversity of Kalemin featured prominently in the histories before the great war, and will continue to be a thing well into the future, relative to our story.
In fact, two entirely new races were created by the gods either directly before or during the conflict: The Scourge (who will later be called humans) and dragonkin.
Also, our protagonist is a dwarf, so doubly wrong for this game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other two, however, are worth consideration.
In my mind, the great dwarven empire was not especially xenophobic, so I have always imagined that there were probably many pockets of non-dwarven folk scattered about, particularly considering that its control spanned a geographical area roughly the size of Mexico. 
Ultimate sovereignty over all territory within the empire lay with the dwarves of course, but they weren’t too greedy to let others live there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s undoubtedly an argument for these people of other races to be fiercely protective of their territory, now that the empire has fallen and it’s properly &lt;em&gt;theirs&lt;/em&gt; to control.
Who could fault them?
I suppose the most important question, then, is how tightly did the dwarves exercise their authority over these other folks?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another consideration is that perhaps, rather than becoming radically territorial, they simply expanded out of their assigned areas. 
Maybe they either weren’t too salty about the past, or the empire wasn’t too hard on them in the first place.
They would certainly exert more control over their domains than before, but might not be outright aggressive toward the dwarves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a move that will surprise no one who read the first two parts of this series, I have decided to make some edits and smash 2/3 of the options together. We end up with this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The old empire held dominion over these lands long ago.
But since it fell, the elves of the deep forests, giants of the hills, and several other racial groups have expanded their influence.
Although some live in isolation and are fiercely protective of their territory, most trade with us and aren’t especially hostile…
for now at least.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my mental picture of the Great Dwarven Empire (as yet unnamed), the dwarves are honorable rulers.
It is this honor which will later, after the fall, lead some toward lives as Ironsworn.
Taking that under consideration, it only makes sense, at least to me, that these other races would be generally neutral at worst toward them.
Of course, some would have grabbed as much land as possible and will have become increasingly fervent about holding onto it with white-knuckled fists (or hairy-knuckled, green-knuckled, etc).
Most, though, would simply be happy in their fresh independence and hold no ill will toward the dwarves who did much to provide infrastructure and resources to all their subjects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least that’s what the dwarves tell themselves. We’ll see how that pans out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;beasts&quot;&gt;Beasts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What dangers lurk in the places between places? Let’s talk about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;BEASTS&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The beasts of old are nothing but legend. A few who travel into the deep forests and high mountains return with wild tales of monstrous creatures, but they are obviously delusional. No such things exist.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Monstrous beasts stalk the wild areas of the Ironlands.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Beasts of all sorts roam the Ironlands. They dwell primarily in the reaches, but range into the settled lands to hunt. There, they often prey on cattle, but attacks on travelers, caravans, or even settlements are not uncommon.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We talked before about how these options represent dials and levers we can manipulate to tune our setting the way we want it. You may have noticed that most of the lists are set up like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;TOPIC&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A little bit of it.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A medium amount of it.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A lot of it. A &lt;strong&gt;whole&lt;/strong&gt; lot of it. Crank it up to 11.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t feel bad if that didn’t jump out at you. I only noticed it while I was writing this very article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s probably fairly obvious which of these options we’re going with, given what we know about the history of the region and considering that I let slip in the very first introductory article that our protagonist is a “Slayer of Beasts.”
Let’s discuss it anyway, because there are reasons why it’s obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as the great fortresses and awe-inspiring mountainous statues have crumbled, so too has the peace and safety imposed by the empire fallen to dust.
There are small pockets of civilization which have grown up over the last century or two, but between and around these areas lie the wild places.
In the absence of an orderly government and all its trappings, the wilderness has expanded and absorbed the pristine stone roads and tame forest valleys from the golden age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That definitely knocks “nothing but legend” out of the running, but what about the other two?
We know that the new dwarven people are back on the path toward taming their surroundings once more and rebuilding something akin to a proper society.
How far have we come on that road, though?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think there’s a beautiful asymmetry between the relatively advanced state of civic organization that we saw in the second article, and an untamed wilderness with beastly apex predators running loose on the fringes.
This paints a picture of a society with some infrastructure in place to fight against the wild, but it’s a battle which has only just begun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must confess at this point that I’ve been omitting something throughout this series, mostly for the sake of brevity. Each option for every truth includes a Quest Starter - a possible prompt for the start of the game.
This might inform your background vow, or it may fuel your inciting incident.
It’s really up to you.
The third entry in this section has this as its quest starter:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Quest Starter: Professional slayers earn their keep by killing beasts. This particular slayer, famed throughout the Ironlands for
her numerous kills, has gone missing on a hunt. Did she finally meet her match, or is something more nefarious at play. What
is your connection to her?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I read that, it sang to me. Consider yourself foreshadowed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the event that you haven’t guessed yet, the third option is the one for us, because of course we’re going to 11.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;horrors&quot;&gt;Horrors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on your frame of reference, there may or may not be much difference between beasts and monsters in your mind.
I want to make sure that we start with the same understanding about the differences between these terms as I will be using them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A beast is something natural. Regardless of whether or not it poses a threat to the safety or property of our people, it is &lt;em&gt;of the world&lt;/em&gt;. That doesn’t mean that there can’t be beasts in our story that are fantastical and strange compared to the sorts of things we have in our world, just that all such things which are considered beasts come from nature and have a place in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Horrors (or monsters - I will be using these interchangeably), are different things entirely.
A monster is something &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt;.
Maybe its origins are demonic in nature, or perhaps it is something that was created by the gods to fight in their war.
It might have once been a beast, but has been fundamentally changed in some way, perhaps through exposure to raw and potent magic. 
Not a part of the natural order of things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are we on the same wavelength now? Excellent!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;HORRORS&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Nothing but stories to frighten children.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;We are wary of dark forests and deep waterways, for monsters lurk in those places. In the depths of the long-night, when all is wreathed in darkness, only fools venture beyond their homes.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The dead do not rest in the Ironlands. At night we light torches, scatter salt, and post sentries at the gate. It is not enough.
They are coming.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the aftermath of a war between gods, we can safely rule out the first option. They created dragons, so who’s to say that other monstrous creatures were out of the question?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shuluk, was one of the two deities who presided over the dead.
Unlike her counterpart, Hennus, she was less straight-laced about it.
Known by some as She Who Calls The Sleepers, Shuluk was also seen as the goddess of undeath.
Her armies were made up of corpses of fallen combatants at least as often as by the living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That may make it seem like I’m steering us toward the “dead do not rest” option, but I’m actually doing the opposite.
Because Shuluk was on the losing side, and like the rest of the gods who were defeated, she was banished from Kalemin.
There may still be undead in some places.
Perhaps there are sorcerers about who can create or command them, or who even strive to become undead themselves.
However, these things are not the norm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There certainly are monsters lurking in the world, though.
If you add these horrors to the beasts we already know about, the interstices between settled lands can be quite frightening and dangerous indeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The middle road will steer us best I think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion-and-summary&quot;&gt;Conclusion and Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it! We’ve made it through worldbuilding, and hopefully you can see now how this relatively short list of multiple choice questions can help inspire a vast and varied array of different worlds.
To reiterate a point that I made in an earlier article, this only seems like a huge task due to the format and my penchant for longwindedness (or if you want to be charitable, my dedication to giving a thorough representation of my thought process).
I will let you in on a secret: I actually did this whole exercise well before I ever conceived of the idea for this blog.
The entirety of the ground that we’ve spent three entries covering took ten minutes in my head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If even that is longer than you can wait before diving into creating your character, that’s fine too.
You could make the character first, then build the world as necessary in your own story.
Or, you could create both the world and your character at the same time.
Ironsworn is extremely flexible that way.
In fact, the entire worldbuilding exercise is optional.
It’s all narrative and doesn’t directly impact the game’s mechanics (I don’t recommend skipping it entirely though).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of character creation, I’m more than a little excited for our next article in which we will finally meet our protagonist, Ida Eisenbaum. We’ll be going through the process from start to finish and find out who she is, what she can do, and maybe even why she does it. I can’t wait!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;postscript---our-truths&quot;&gt;Postscript - Our Truths&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below, you’ll find a collected list of our truths that we’ve been building over the last three articles.
They are compiled so that we can easily reference them later if we need to double check something, or just need some inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;THE OLD WORLD &lt;br /&gt;
The legends say there was once a glorious empire. But that was before the gods warred among themselves, and brought the fight to these lands. The savage Scourge and their lords flooded over it. The grand armies fell, along with the ancient fortresses and deep cities. Those who survived found themselves in a land bereft of the order and majesty of the old days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;IRON &lt;br /&gt;
The imposing hills and mountains of these lands are rich in iron ore. Most prized of all is the star-forged black iron.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;LEGACIES &lt;br /&gt;
The ancient empire’s bones are scattered all around. The husks of great fortresses provide shelter to the things which hide from the sun, and the giant statues adorning the sides of the mountains remind us that our ancestors were once great and powerful. But that was long, long ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;COMMUNITIES &lt;br /&gt;
We live in communities called circles. These are settlements ranging in size from a steading with a few families to a village of several hundred. Some circles belong to nomadic folk. Some powerful circles might include a cluster of settlements. We trade (and sometimes feud) with other circles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;LEADERSHIP &lt;br /&gt;
Most of our communities are governed by their own leader, called an overseer. As our traditions from before the war dictate, every seventh spring, the people affirm their current overseer or choose a new one. Some overseers wear the iron circlet reluctantly, while others thirst for power and gain it through schemes or threats.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Not everyone chooses to follow the old ways, though.
There are places ruled by warlords.
There are wandering clans whose leadership is decided by combat.
There are even rumors of a group that lives high in the peaks whose leader is chosen by a sacred bird.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;DEFENSE&lt;br /&gt;
Here among the ruins, supplies are too precious, and the lands are too sparsely populated, to support organized fighting forces.
When a community is threatened, the people stand together to protect their own.
Instead, we have wardens.
The wardens are our hunters and our protectors.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;They serve their communities by standing sentry, patrolling surrounding lands, and organizing defenses in times of crisis. They often range far from their communities in search of threats (and game), and occasionally cross paths with wardens from other settlements. In the absense of traders, this is how we get our news and knowledge of the world beyond our little pieces of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;MYSTICISM &lt;br /&gt;
Some still find comfort in the old ways. They call on mystics to divine the fortune of their newborn, or ask them to perform rituals to invoke a bountiful harvest. Others act out of fear against those who they suspect of having power.
However, most folk believe true magic—if it ever existed—is lost to us now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;RELIGION &lt;br /&gt;
The people honor old gods and new. In this harsh land, a prayer is a simple but powerful comfort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;FIRSTBORN &lt;br /&gt;
The old empire held dominion over these lands long ago.
But since it fell, the elves of the deep forests, giants of the hills, and several other racial groups have expanded their influence.
Although some live in isolation and are fiercely protective of their territory, most trade with us and aren’t especially hostile…
for now at least.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;BEASTS &lt;br /&gt;
Beasts of all sorts roam the ruined lands. They dwell primarily in the reaches, but range into the settled lands to hunt. There, they often prey on cattle, but attacks on travelers, caravans, or even settlements are not uncommon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;HORRORS &lt;br /&gt;
We are wary of dark forests and deep waterways, for monsters lurk in those places. In the depths of the long-night, when all is wreathed in darkness, only fools venture beyond their homes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In Part I, we discussed what the land is like, and a bit of history. Then we learned some important things about our people in Part II. Definitely check those out if you missed them, because they will inform many decisions we make moving forward.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Worldbuilding Part II - The People</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/worldbuilding-part-ii-the-people/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Worldbuilding Part II - The People" /><published>2019-02-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-02-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/worldbuilding-part-ii-the-people</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/worldbuilding-part-ii-the-people/">&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the second part of our worldbuilding series in which we are, as Bob Ross would put it, making some big decisions.
If you missed Part I, I recommend &lt;a href=&quot;/worldbuilding-part-i-the-land/&quot;&gt;checking it out&lt;/a&gt;.
It might be confusing otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last time, we worked out the history of our setting and a bit of color here and there.
Of course, an RPG setting wouldn’t be very conducive to RP without people. 
Let’s figure out who they are and how they live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;communities&quot;&gt;Communities&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;COMMUNITIES&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;We are few in number in this accursed land. Most rarely have contact with anyone outside our own small steading or village, and strangers are viewed with deep suspicion.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;We live in communities called circles. These are settlements ranging in size from a steading with a few families to a village of several hundred. Some circles belong to nomadic folk. Some powerful circles might include a cluster of settlements. We trade (and sometimes feud) with other circles.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;We have forged the Ironlands into a home. Villages within the Havens are connected by well-trod roads. Trade caravans travel between settlements in the Havens and those in outlying regions. Even so, much of this land is untamed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things I really like about this worldbuilding system is that it’s full of levers and dials that you can tweak to end up with wildly different worlds, even if you use the stock campaign setting.
Do you want to play in a world where the people live in small, insular groups? Or would you prefer something more akin to clans? Or, are you more interested in the dynamics that cities and trade can give you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this game were going to be happening more directly after the great war, the first option would probably be the best one.
I think instead, we will begin in the time when dwarven society is just starting to get back on its feet.
The third option is the other extreme, and we definitely aren’t back to a place where the land is tamed again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not too hard and not too soft. The middle option is just right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;leaders&quot;&gt;Leaders&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we have middling communities, which might be collections of dwarven clans who have banded together.
But how do these communities opperate?
You can learn a great deal about a culture based on how they govern themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;LEADERS&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Leadership is as varied as the people. Some communities are governed by the head of a powerful family. Or, they have a council of elders who make decisions and settle disputes. In others, the priests hold sway. For some, it is duels in the circle that decide.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Each of our communities has its own leader, called an overseer. Every seventh spring, the people affirm their current overseer or choose a new one. Some overseers wear the iron circlet reluctantly, while others thirst for power and gain it through schemes or threats.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Numerous clan-chiefs rule over petty domains. Most are intent on becoming the one true king. Their squabbles will be our undoing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up to this point, I’ve had a pretty easy time figuring out which option I wanted to pick, but these are all very exciting choices.
One of them even has “clan” in it!
This is going to be a tough call, so let’s think through them one by one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;leadership-is-varied&quot;&gt;Leadership is varied…&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first option could give us a pretty broad pallette with which to paint our story.
In one village, there might be some akin to a mayor, elected by his people.
Nearby we might find a valley with several villages all ruled by a despot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pros: Lots of potential for variety&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cons: I like the idea of having generally understood customs and expectations that Ida can work with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;each-community-has-an-elected-leader&quot;&gt;Each community has an elected leader&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one has a distinctly orderly feel to it, and it gels with my mental model of what these dwarves are like. Maybe this form of government is a cultural hold-over from the time before the war? It feels fairly enlightened. On the other hand, the dwarven lands are quite expansive and it’s difficult to imagine that &lt;em&gt;everyone&lt;/em&gt; ended up with the same structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pros: Consistent with what I think a nascent cultural revival might look like, and I can see this form of government providing the springboard the dwarves need to start climbing back to where they used to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cons: Perhaps a little &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; consistent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;clan-chiefs&quot;&gt;Clan-chiefs&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really, the only thing going for this one in my mind is that it has “clan” in it.
I think it’s definitely possible that this might be where this young civilization will end up in the future, it’s a little early for it now.
Also, I think there’s more than enough danger to be had without folks fighting over land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pros: for this setting, almost none.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cons: all of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;decision&quot;&gt;Decision&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the most interesting option is a marriage of the first two choices:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Most of our communities are governed by their own leader, called an overseer. As our traditions from before the war dictate, every seventh spring, the people affirm their current overseer or choose a new one. Some overseers wear the iron circlet reluctantly, while others thirst for power and gain it through schemes or threats.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Not everyone chooses to follow the old ways, though.
There are places ruled by warlords.
There are wandering clans whose leadership is decided by combat.
There are even rumors of a group that lives high in the peaks whose leader is chosen by a sacred bird.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like this because it gives us most of the pros, yet mitigates the cons.  That’s what we’ll go with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;defense&quot;&gt;Defense&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is another one of those lever-and-dial situations, as you’ll see. Just how stable and safe are settled lands and the places in between?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;DEFENSE&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Here in the Ironlands, supplies are too precious, and the lands are too sparsely populated, to support organized fighting forces. When a community is threatened, the people stand together to protect their own.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The wardens are our soldiers, guards, and militia. They serve their communities by standing sentry, patrolling surrounding lands, and organizing defenses in times of crisis. Most have strong ties to their community. Others, called free wardens, are wandering mercenaries who hire on to serve a community or protect caravans.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Our warbands are rallied to strike at our enemies or defend our holdings. Though not nearly as impressive as the armies that once marched across the Old World, these forces are as well-trained and equipped as their communities can manage. The banners of the warbands are adorned with depictions of their Old World history and Ironland victories.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think we’ve covered why the last option is out, so we’ll just leave that one be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s an interesting argument to be made about the middle one. The concept that’s been percolating in my head for Ida is that she’s a hunter of beasts, maybe even some kind of…well, warden.
I imagine her to be not unlike your archetypal ranger as far as her duties are concerned, so perhaps this one might fit.
Before we make a snap judgement, though, let’s have a think about the first item.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We mentioned before that the land is rich in minerals and what not.
Then again, people don’t eat minerals.
Has the land recovered from the ravages of the war, or are food and clean water still hard to come by?
I think there is room for some lovely juxtaposition between resource scarcity and the “enlightened” governing structure we chose before. I imagine people with dirt under their fingernails, trying to scrape by and build themselves back up to something resembling stability, while at the same time clinging to old traditions as a reminder of who they once were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe, as before, there’s room for a compromise here. In general, the land is sparsely populated. There aren’t great lines of supply and trade yet, so there certainly aren’t standing armies. Probably not even sizeable militias.  Maybe some of the larger circles have found a decent place with sufficient access to the necessities to have dedicated protectors, though. Nothing standardized or codified in any charter or anything, but perhaps ubiquitous enough that wardens from different settlements sometimes run across each other and share news and knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Here among the ruins, supplies are too precious, and the lands are too sparsely populated, to support organized fighting forces.
When a community is threatened, the people stand together to protect their own.
Instead, we have wardens.
The wardens are our hunters and our protectors.
They serve their communities by standing sentry, patrolling surrounding lands, and organizing defenses in times of crisis. They often range far from their communities in search of threats (and game), and occasionally cross paths with wardens from other settlements. In the absense of traders, this is how we get our news and knowledge of the world beyond our little pieces of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mysticism&quot;&gt;Mysticism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironsworn is generally a low-magic game.
In the stock rules, there are no big, flashy spells to cast.
Instead, there are Rituals you can use, which have significantly subtler effects.
However, this is yet another configuration option of sorts you can set as you choose.
It doesn’t change the character options you have available (at least not the ones the game comes with out of the box) but it does affect the world around you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;MYSTICISM&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Some still find comfort in the old ways. They call on mystics to divine the fortune of their newborn, or ask them to perform rituals to invoke a bountiful harvest. Others act out of fear against those who they suspect of having power.
However, most folk believe true magic—if it ever existed—is lost to us now.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Magic is rare and dangerous, but those few who wield the power are truly gifted.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Magic courses through this land as the rivers flow through the hills. The power is there for those who choose to harness it,
and even the common folk often know a helpful ritual or two.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lore of Kalemin contains a great deal of overt and powerful magic.
The Dwarves there, however,  are not well known for their use of powerful sorcery.
I find myself at a bit of an impasse.
There is indeed magic coursing through the land as described in the third option, but I don’t know that I want that to be a major thematic element of this game.
I think instead that we’ll use the first option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps there is a great deal of magic for those who might know how to wield it, but that’s simply not who the dwarves are. Their magic is tied to rituals, runes, and divination. In general, we’ll be using the first option, with the understanding that there might be other characters down the road which demonstrate one of the other options is also possibly true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;religion&quot;&gt;Religion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;RELIGION&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A few Ironlanders still make signs or mumble prayers out of habit or tradition, but most believe the gods long ago abandoned us.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The people honor old gods and new. In this harsh land, a prayer is a simple but powerful comfort.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Our gods are many. They make themselves known through manifestations and miracles. Some say they even secretly walk among us. The priests convey the will of the gods and hold sway over many communities.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kalemin is a world in which the existence of deities is pretty much a given.
Most cultures and peoples across the world follow the same deities (although they may have different names for them).
However, the history, and our gameplay experiences in the world in other games, have led us to the conclusion that the gods have stepped back from direct intervention following the pantheon war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, while the third option was once true, it is more likely that the second one is the best here. This game will be set fairly close to the conclusion of the war between the gods, so there will be those who remember a time in which the gods performed miracles (and sometimes atrocities). However, that is no longer the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the people do still pray.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;to-be-concluded&quot;&gt;To be concluded…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we add more brush strokes to this world’s canvas, I imagine an image of our setting emerging from the dark background.
We’ve figured out what kind of land we’re in, and what kind of people live there.
We have but a few more choices to make and we’ll be ready to dig into character creation and start play in earnest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But first, we get to decide what sorts of external circumstances we might run into along the way. It should be quite exciting indeed!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Welcome to the second part of our worldbuilding series in which we are, as Bob Ross would put it, making some big decisions. If you missed Part I, I recommend checking it out. It might be confusing otherwise.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Worldbuilding Part I - The Land</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/worldbuilding-part-i-the-land/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Worldbuilding Part I - The Land" /><published>2019-02-11T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-02-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/worldbuilding-part-i-the-land</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/worldbuilding-part-i-the-land/">&lt;p&gt;I think that it will be easier to get a good picture of who our protagonist will be if we first understand where she is coming from, in the literal sense.
Ironsworn has a built-in setting with a nice set of options for several decision points on the specifics.
I really like the way it’s set up, but I think I’d prefer to play in my group’s homebrew setting, Kalemin, instead.
Since I and my group created it, I know that setting fairly well. I also know that there are still many blank spots in the lore and the map to explore.
As I was reading through the world creation options, though, I discovered a pleasant surprise: If I set up the game at the right place in the right time, I don’t even have to do much editing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because there are a whopping 11 categories to go through, and because many of them require a fair bit of discussion and consideration, I’ve decided to break up worldbuilding into three separate posts. This one will cover the land and how these people came to live here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might sound like a lot to get through in order to play, but it only seems that way due to the medium. In practice, the worldbuilding exercise can be completed in about 5-10 minutes tops when you’re not writing about it and discussing each bit in detail. But my goal here is to bring you on this journey with me and give you as authentic a representation of how I think as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve read several excellent chronicles of solo RPGs, but something I have always wanted, but rarely found, are accounts of all the things that happen before and between the fiction. So here we are!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s dig in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;our-truths&quot;&gt;Our Truths&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned before, worldbuilding in Ironsworn is done by choosing an option in several categories, which, when combined, give you a colorful and evocative setting.
If you’d like to follow along, the world workbook is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ironswornrpg.com/downloads&quot;&gt;available for free&lt;/a&gt; (along with just about everything else related to the game).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-old-world&quot;&gt;The Old World&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth we choose here tells us about where the people in the Ironlands came from. 
Before we jump right into the custom setting I mentioned above, let’s have a peek at what this concept looks like as intended:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;THE OLD WORLD&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The savage clans called the Skulde invaded the kingdoms of the Old World. Our armies fell. Most were killed or taken into slavery. Those who escaped set sail aboard anything that would float. After an arduous months-long voyage, the survivors made landfall upon the Ironlands.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The sickness moved like a horrible wave across the Old World, killing all in its path. Thousands fled aboard ships. However, the plague could not be outrun. On many ships, the disease was contained through ruthless measures—tossing overboard any who exhibited the slightest symptom. Other ships were forever lost. In the end, those who survived found the Ironlands and made it their new home. Some say we will forever be cursed by those we left behind.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The Old World could no longer sustain us. We were too large in number. We had felled the forests. Our crops withered in the barren ground. The cities and villages overflowed with desperate, hungry people. Petty kings battled for scraps. We cast our fate to the sea and found the Ironlands. A new world. A fresh start.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems that the idea is for the Ironlands to be a frontier, or at least not the place where the Ironlanders are originally from.
In Kalemin’s history, there was a catastrophic war in the distant past relative to my group’s other campaigns.
In that war, the pantheon split and waged a civil war, which played out on the mortal plane.
Instead of having the game take place in a “new world,” we’re going to be playing in the ruins of the old one (thus the name of the blog). I’m thinking perhaps a hundred years or so following the final apocalyptic battles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the options above is pretty close to the image I have in my head. With a decent bit of tweaking, here’s what we get:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The legends say there was once a glorious empire. But that was before the gods warred among themselves, and brought the fight to these lands. The savage Scourge and their lords flooded over it. The grand armies fell, along with the ancient fortresses and deep cities. Those who survived found themselves in a land bereft of the order and majesty of the old days.						
It is at this point that you may realize that Kalemin is not nearly as low-fantasy as the Ironlands.
I originally created it for a Dungeons and Dragons campaign, and thus all the D&amp;amp;D races are represented for the most part. 
The empire referenced here is that of the dwarves. Ida is a dwarven woman. Surprise!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For additional context, the Scourge will later become known as humans, and “their lords” refer to the dragons who led them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;iron&quot;&gt;Iron&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;/introduction&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;, we talked about how swearing a vow on iron is a big deal. The options presented below will give us the opportunity to figure out why:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;IRON&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The imposing hills and mountains of the Ironlands are rich in iron ore. Most prized of all is the star-forged black iron.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The weather is bleak. Rain and wind sweep in from the ocean. The winters are long and bitter. One of the first settlers complained, “Only those made of iron dare live in this foul place”—and thus our land was named.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Inscrutable metal pillars are found throughout the land. They are iron gray, and smooth as river stone. No one knows their purpose. Some say they are as old as the world. Some, such as the Iron Priests, worship them and swear vows upon them. Most make the warding sign and hurry along their way when they happen across one. The pillars do not tarnish, and even the sharpest blade cannot mark them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most fantasy settings in which dwarves appear, metalworking is a common focus among them.
This is true of the dwarves of Kalemin.
Iron, therefore, is pretty important. We’re just going to go with the first one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a common trope of post-apocalyptic fantasy that I thing we can get some decent mileage out of for our purposes: The destruction was so complete that a great deal of advanced knowledge was lost.
For instance, we don’t know how the black iron was forged anymore.
The techniques were lost, probably due to the destruction of the original equipment and lack of resources required to make it.
The sparse population that survived the war was too busy trying to survive and it simply faded from the collective minds of the dwarves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being a people inclined toward working with metal, iron would be quite important and valuable. We also have an additional layer to explore later if we want to: Who has black iron and what is it worth? What legends speak of it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will, of course, play to find out what happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;legacies&quot;&gt;Legacies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Legacies in the Ironlands refer to who and what used to be in the new world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;LEGACIES&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;We are the first humans to walk these lands.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Other humans sailed here from the Old World untold years ago, but all that is left of them is a savage, feral people we call the broken. Is their fate to become our own?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Before the Ironlanders, before even the firstborn, another people lived here. Their ancient ruins are found throughout the Ironlands.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve already decided that the lands we live in are the same lands our ancestors lived in, so many of these don’t apply. 
Due to our divergence from the “new world” that the Ironlands setting is supposed to be, we get to expand on our Truth about The Old World instead:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The ancient empire’s bones are scattered all around. The husks of great fortresses provide shelter to the things which hide from the sun, and the giant statues adorning the sides of the mountains remind us that our ancestors were once great and powerful. But that was long, long ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paints a pretty grim picture of what the world is like now.
We can expect to see vast ruins and other hints that the land was once tamed, but it is now broken and dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And exciting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;to-be-continued&quot;&gt;To Be Continued…&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it for the land itself. Next time, we’re going to talk about the people and how they live. Will there be democracy? Monarchy? Despotic warlords? We shall see!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I think that it will be easier to get a good picture of who our protagonist will be if we first understand where she is coming from, in the literal sense. Ironsworn has a built-in setting with a nice set of options for several decision points on the specifics. I really like the way it’s set up, but I think I’d prefer to play in my group’s homebrew setting, Kalemin, instead. Since I and my group created it, I know that setting fairly well. I also know that there are still many blank spots in the lore and the map to explore. As I was reading through the world creation options, though, I discovered a pleasant surprise: If I set up the game at the right place in the right time, I don’t even have to do much editing.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Introduction</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/introduction/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introduction" /><published>2019-02-06T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-02-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/introduction</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/introduction/">&lt;p&gt;Welcome to From the Ashes, an Ironsworn blog.  Ironsworn is a Powered by the Apocalypse game created by Shawn Tomkin. It was designed from the ground up to be played in several different ways: Guided (with a GM), cooperatively (multiple players without a GM), or solo (single player, no GM). This blog will contain accounts of solo gameplay by yours truly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solo aspect of Ironsworn is what really drew me to it. I’ve tried solo tabletop games in the past, but nothing &lt;em&gt;sang&lt;/em&gt; to me. Some games felt like a slightly crunchier choose-your-own-adventure book, while others were a bit too far on the rules light side of things and ended up feeling more like writing a novel than playing an RPG.  From what I can tell having done some exploratory testing, Ironsworn hits a sweet spot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several aspects of the game that help it achieve its solo goals.  We’ll be discussing a few of them here: Moves, the Oracle, and Vows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;moves&quot;&gt;Moves&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the moves, as in most PbtA games, are set up so that you never just &lt;em&gt;fail&lt;/em&gt; at something. If the dice don’t go your way, something always changes. For example, in more traditional tabletop games, if you fail to pick a lock, you’re still standing in the corridor facing a locked door. Nothing is different. It is as if you never tried at all. In a PbtA game, rolling a “miss” (what it’s called instead of a failure, for reasons which will become clear soon), doesn’t necessarily mean you fail at the thing you were trying to do. And even if you do fail, something in the situation changes. There are no null outcomes.  For instance, using the same example, you attempt to pick the lock. You roll the dice and it comes up bad. Maybe you fail, but you hear guards coming down the hallway. Or maybe you succeed, but find something ominous on the other side rather than the treasure you thought would be there. This “fail forward” approach to game mechanics ensures that, assuming you’re following the rules, you can never hit a stalemate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another common thread among PbtA games is that a roll doesn’t give you a binary outcome (e.g. hit/miss).
There are three possible results: a strong hit, a weak hit, and a miss.
We covered misses already.
Strong hits are the “ideal” outcome for your character.
You get what you were going for.
This can be fun without a doubt, but the third outcome is often far more interesting.
You can think of a weak hit as success with a drawback.
You managed to get out of the estate without alerting the guards, but you realize once you’re outside that you left something behind that, if found, will tip them off.
Usually, moves are set up in one of several ways.
First, the move might be set up such that there are a number of positive outcomes you can choose, and the stronger your hit, the more you get to pick.
For instance, here is the &lt;strong&gt;Make Camp&lt;/strong&gt; move from Ironsworn:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MAKE CAMP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;When you rest and recover for several hours in the wild, roll +supply. On a strong hit, you and your allies may each choose two. On a weak hit, choose one.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Recuperate: Take +1 health for you and any companions.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Partake: Suffer -1 supply and take +1 health for you and any companions.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Relax: Take +1 spirit.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Focus: Take +1 momentum.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Prepare: When you break camp, add +1 if you Undertake a Journey.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;On a miss, you take no comfort. &lt;em&gt;Pay the Price&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, the better your roll, the more good things you get to pick.
Conversely, there are also moves where a weak hit gives you bad outcomes to choose among.
You have the narrative control to decide in exactly what way your character will have a bad time.
A good example of this is the &lt;strong&gt;End the Fight&lt;/strong&gt; move:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;END THE FIGHT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;When you make a move to take decisive action, and score a strong hit, you may resolve the outcome of this fight. If you do, roll the challenge dice and compare to your progress. Momentum is ignored on this roll.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;On a strong hit, this foe is no longer in the fight. They are killed, out of action, flee, or surrender as appropriate to the situation and your intent (Ask the Oracle if unsure).&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;On a weak hit, as above, but you must also choose one.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;It’s worse than you thought: &lt;em&gt;Endure Harm&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;You are overcome: &lt;em&gt;Endure Stress&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Your victory is short-lived: A new danger or foe appears, or an existing danger worsens.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;You suffer collateral damage: Something of value is lost or broken, or someone important must pay the cost.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;You’ll pay for it: An objective falls out of reach.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Others won’t forget: You are marked for vengeance.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;On a miss, you have lost this fight. &lt;em&gt;Pay the Price&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most PbtA games, these mechanics add a dynamic level of excitement to the narrative and give you more knobs and levers to tweak in order to tell the kind of story you’re trying to tell as a group.
In a solo game, however, this sort of thing is pure gold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironsworn takes this weak hit idea and cranks it up a notch by fiddling with the statistical probabilities.
You see, most PbtA games run on a 2d6 system with fixed targets.
You roll 2d6, add your stat, and see what the result is.
A 10+ is a strong hit, 7-9 is a weak hit, and 6- is a miss. Statistically, the most common dice totals are 6, 7, and 8.
Thus, with +0-2, you’re likely to hit in that middle range a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt;.
 In practice, what happens is that, as your character progresses, you end up with more and more 10+ results and fewer 7-9 results.
 A story in which the heroes are always awesome can get boring.
 That goes double when you’re the only person playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than a 2d6 system with fixed targets, Ironsworn uses 1d6 vs two d10s (not 2d10, because that would be absurd).
It works like this: You roll your &lt;em&gt;action die&lt;/em&gt; (the d6) and add your stats and any other bonuses you might have.
You then roll your &lt;em&gt;challenge dice&lt;/em&gt; (the d10s).
If your action total beats both challenge dice, it’s a strong hit.
If you only beat one of them, it’s a weak hit.
If you don’t beat either, it’s a miss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That might be confusing, so let’s look at some examples.
Let’s say your applicable stat is +1, and you have a +1 bonus for some reason.
You roll the action die and get 2, for a total of 4.
You then roll the challenge dice, which come up 2 and 3, a strong hit because you beat both dice.
If instead, the challenge dice come up 3 and 6, it’s a weak hit, because you beat the 3, but not the 6.
If they come up 4 and 5, it’s a miss because your 4 doesn’t beat either of them (your 4 is not greater than either challenge die).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another fun addition to this mechanic is that you can never have more than a total of +4 to your roll, which means that the highest action total you can get is 10.
Since you lose ties with the challenge dice, you can never get to a point where a miss is impossible (unlike in some other PbtA games where you can).
This novel dice mechanic in conjunction with the structure of the moves result in highly dynamic, and often surprising, gameplay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-oracle&quot;&gt;The Oracle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The astute reader might have noticed the presence of “Ask the Oracle if unsure” in the &lt;em&gt;End the Fight&lt;/em&gt; move above.
 As mentioned before, Ironsworn was written from the beginning to allow for GM-less play.
 &lt;strong&gt;Ask the Oracle&lt;/strong&gt; is a move which facilitates using the numerous tables in the book to generate narrative outcomes or simply spark ideas.
 This is done by rolling percentile dice.
 You might ask the oracle if the town you just arrived in has any horses for sale.
 You decide that it’s unlikely, but not unheard of.
 You assign it a level of “unlikely” (25% chance) and let the dice decide.
 You might instead ask the oracle what motivations the bandit leader has as you converse with them.
 You decide to use a combination of tables to gain some inspiration.
 You roll on the Theme table and get “Revenge,” and on the Action table and get “Reject.
  Perhaps this bandit leader was exiled from the nearby village and decided to squeeze the trade routes to get back at them.
  Or maybe they were jilted by the one whose love they desired, and are using banditry as a way to lash out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With oracle tables for all kinds of things, such as Theme and Action, as well as Settlement Trouble, Location Descriptor, Combat Action, and a host of others, it’s easy to see how this would be highly useful to a solo player.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;iron-vows&quot;&gt;Iron Vows&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironsworn’s Vows also work to ensure that there’s always something to do.
They’re effectively quests with varying degrees of difficulty.
As an Ironsworn, you swear vows on iron (literally, you hold something made of iron and speak your vow).
Depending on what choices you make when creating your setting, this could be an invocation of mystical power that binds you to your word.
Or, it could simply be related to a strong sense of honor in your setting.
Whatever it means to you, oaths made on iron are &lt;em&gt;important&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You begin with a background vow, an oath you made at some point before the game begins.
This isn’t the sort of thing that you’re going to get done any time soon.
It’s more like a long-term goal, something for your character to work toward throughout the course of the game.
You also begin with some inciting incident which leads to your swearing another Iron Vow.
This is intended to give you something to immediately go and do.
Throughout the course of the game, you’ll be meeting new people who will want you to do things.
Sometimes these things will progress one or more of your vows.
Sometimes it will be more of a “you scratch my back and I’ll scratch yours” situation in order to gain the aid of a character.
No matter what the reason, it’s quite easy to keep yourself filled to the brim with oaths to keep (and thus more stories to tell).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iron Vows are more than just narrative tools, though.
The only way in which you can gain experience points (and thus character advancement) is through completing vows.
It’s a fine marriage of carrot and stick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s next?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the near future, I’ll be setting up for an Ironsworn game which will take place here.
The first series of posts will cover worldbuilding, in which we will decide what kind of environment we’ll be playing in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like what you’ve been reading about Ironsworn so far, or you just want to follow along with the mechanics as I play, Ironsworn is &lt;a href=&quot;https://ironswornrpg.com&quot;&gt;available here&lt;/a&gt; for the utterly unbeatable price of &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;free&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.
You can get the core rulebook, character sheet, and a whole slew of other helpful things for exactly zero money.
Having read the entire thing and played the game a bit, I can tell you that I would have no buyer’s remorse if I’d paid $40-50 for it.
But nope, it was free.
I highly recommend checking it out, and if you decide you really love it, you can head over to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/238369/Ironsworn?src=Zenith&quot;&gt;DriveThruRPG&lt;/a&gt; and throw some money at the designer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And make sure to keep an eye out for the next post where we will make some big decisions about our game’s setting and begin the journey toward meeting our protagonist: Ida Eisenbaum, Slayer of Beasts!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Welcome to From the Ashes, an Ironsworn blog. Ironsworn is a Powered by the Apocalypse game created by Shawn Tomkin. It was designed from the ground up to be played in several different ways: Guided (with a GM), cooperatively (multiple players without a GM), or solo (single player, no GM). This blog will contain accounts of solo gameplay by yours truly.</summary></entry></feed>